Michael Lee

Data Visualization Developer

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

4+ years applying open source libraries to analyze data and build products that drive knowledge acquisition and decision making. Whether working independently or collaboratively I'm able to contribute meaningful work through strong communication skills, critically evaluating challenging data problems, and the attention to diverse audiences across my professional career.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

American Institutes for Research (July 2015 - Present)

- Co-authored the <u>EdSurvey</u> R package for analysis of survey data using NCES statistical methods, including the development of R functions from scratch (with acceptance tests), two vignettes, and presentation of the package's practical use for researchers at 2016, 2017, and 2018 AERA workshops
- Co-authored the NAEPprimer data package
- Collaborated with designers to automate the production of summary reports, each featuring a custom-designed LaTeX template embedded with unique ggplot2 visualizations illustrating data trends
- Wrote R scripts to review data sets in longitudinal surveys to meet compliance standards
- Developed over 10 unique animations for social media distribution at twitter.com/EdNCES

FREELANCE/INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR

The Ballengee Group (November 2014 - February 2015)

- Created a database of baseball performance and salary data exclusively using R software
- Modeled salary expectations for over 80 major and minor league baseball players across a 10 year period using machine learning methods

www.mikelee.co (November 2014 - Present)

 Online portfolio of data visualizations and independent analyses; implemented with Bulma and hosted on GitHub

SPECIAL EDUCATION TEACHER

Milwaukee Public Schools (Aug 2011 - June 2013)

- Utilized performance data to develop lesson plans, activities, and interventions appropriate for students with diverse learning needs and disabilities
- Collaborated with staff to create Individualized Education Programs for students with significant behavioral challenges
- Moderated behavior charts and implemented effective classroom management techniques

EDUCATION

MASTERS OF ARTS. **URBAN EDUCATION**

2013

Cardinal Stritch University. Milwaukee, WI

Washington, DC Phone: 414-550-3410

Email: mdlee12@amail.com

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE. **PSYCHOLOGY**

University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI

SPECIALTIES

Data Analysis & Processing Data Visualization Web Development Web Scraping R Package Development **Technical Writing** Workshop Moderation

SKILLS

Data Toolbox

R // Python // SQL // Shiny // Excel

Web Development

HTML5 // D3.js // CSS // Hugo // Git // Jekyll // Bootstrap

Teaching

Lesson Planning // Workshops // Differentiated Instruction